Finding Aid for Rebecca Shelley Papers 1890-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rebecca Shelley Papers
1890-1984
Shelley, Rebecca, 1887-1984.
86123, Aa/2, UAm
Pacifist, participant in World War I peace movement and later peace activities, member of Fellowship of Reconciliation, Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, and Women Strike for Peace. Papers include Correspondence, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, periodicals, reports, photographs, and other materials relating to the International Congress of Women, 1915, the Ford Peace Ship, the American Neutral Conference Committee, the Emergency Peace Federation, and the People's Council of America.
21 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Rebecca Shelley in several accessions between 1964 and 1984. Donor no. 4218
The collection is open for research.
Rebecca Shelley, Battle Creek pacifist and feminist, was born in Sugar Valley, Pennsylvania in 1887. She attended the Normal School at Clarion, Pennsylvania from 1902 to 1904 and taught briefly in Pennsylvania. In 1904, Rebecca's father, William Alfred Shelly, moved to Leelanau County, Michigan to become pastor of the local Evangelical congregation. Rebecca taught school for two years in the Leelanau County School but quit teaching in 1907 to attend the University of Michigan. She majored in German and graduated Phi Beta Kappa in 1910.
Shelley spent the next five years teaching German in Hayward, Wisconsin (1910-1912), Everett, Washington (1912-1914), and Freeport, Illinois (1914-1915). While traveling with friends in Germany in the summer of 1911, Rebecca met Franz Willman, a German literature and music critic to whom she became engaged in 1913. Their plan had been for Franz to move to the United States, but in August 1914, war was declared and Franz was called to active duty in the German army.
The severity of the world crisis along with her personal situation led her to become a pacifist. When she read about the proposed International Congress of Women at the Hague, Rebecca wrote to Jane Addams and persuaded Addams to allow her to attend as an American delegate. After the conference, Rebecca toured Germany with Angela Morgan, a fellow delegate. In Munich, she met with Franz who died later in the war after contracting encephalitis.
After returning home, Rebecca made numerous contributions to the peace movement. She was a central figure in the Ford Peace Ship (December 1915), the American Neutral Conference Committee (Spring 1916-February 1917), the Emergency Peace Federation (February-July 1917), and the People's Council of America (August 1917-1918).
In 1918, stress and exhaustion forced her to return to Michigan. After recovering at a Battle Creek sanitarium, she settled in Battle Creek. She purchased a trade journal, Modern Poultry Breeder, which she published through most of the 1920s.
In 1922, Rebecca met and married Felix Martin Rathmer, an electrical engineer from Germany. Having married a foreign citizen weeks before the pertinent law expired, Rebecca lost her American citizenship. She then refused to take the naturalization oath which included a clause promising to bear arms in defense of the country. It was only after a lengthy and publicized legal fight that her U.S. citizenship was restored in 1944.
In later years, she again became active in the pacifist movement. She was an organizer of World Peace Month in 1952. In the early 1950s she founded a Battle Creek chapter of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. She was also editor of the Fellowship of Reconciliation's Michigan F.O.R. News for many years.
After the death of her husband in 1959, Rebecca dedicated her Battle Creek property as the Peaceways Foundation. In 1964, she ran for vice-president on a peace party ticket with a Herbert Hoover, a cousin of the former president. From 1968 until 1977, she publicly dressed in mourning as a protest against the Vietnam War. She made extensive tours of Europe and South Asia, conducting peace vigils at embassies and war monuments. In 1984, Rebecca Shelley died at age ninety-seven.
Summary Contents List
Biographical - Box 1
Newspaper Clippings -- 1
Correspondence 1974 accession -- Boxes 1-4 1984 accession -- Boxes 5-7
Topical Papers -- Boxes 7-9
Miscellaneous Papers -- Box 9
Papers of Other individuals -- Box 9
Printed -- Boxes 10-14
Periodicals -- Boxes 14-15
Diaries and Notebooks -- Box 16
Photographs -- Box 17
Writings -- Boxes 17-21
The papers of Rebecca Shelley (1887-1984) were donated by Shelley in several accessions between 1964 and 1984. The papers make up twenty-one linear feet of materials and cover the years 1890-1984, though only a few photographs and printed items predate 1910. Her anti-war activism, legal battles, writing career, and courtships with Franz Willman and Felix Rathmer are all well-represented. In addition to her personal papers, there are groups of material belonging to Emily Balch, Richard Olsen, Felix Rathmer, Paul Shelly, and William A. Shelly.
Many peace organizations are also documented in these papers through flyers, pamphlets, periodicals, newsletters, and correspondence. These include the American Neutral Conference Committee, Emergency Peace Federation, People's Council of America, Fellowship of Reconciliation, Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Women Strike for Peace, and many others. As Shelley served as an officer in the Michigan Fellowship of Reconciliation (F.O.R.) through the 1950s and 1960s, many of the organization's official papers came to be in her possession. Therefore, an effort was made to remove most of these official papers to the separate Michigan F.O.R. collection.
The collection is arranged in eleven series: Biographical; Newspaper Clippings; Correspondence; Topical Papers; Miscellaneous Papers; Papers Of Other Individuals; Printed; Periodicals; Diaries And Notebooks; Photographs; and Writings.
Subjects:
American Civil Liberties Union.; American Neutral Conference Committee.; Battle Creek (Mich.); Conscientious objectors.; Emergency Peace Federation (U.S.); Fellowship of Reconciliation (U.S.); Henry Ford Peace Expedition (1915-1916); German Americans--Michigan.; India.; International Congress of Women (1915: Hague, Netherlands); Peace--Societies, etc.; People's Council of America.; Poetry.; Poultry--Breeding.; Prohibition Party (U.S.). National Committee.; Shelley, Rebecca, 1887-1984.; Social reformers--United States.; Society of Friends--United States.United States.; Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939.; United States. Work Projects Administration.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.Alumni and alumnae.; Vietnam.; Women--United States--Societies and clubs.; Women's rights--United States.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.; Writers' Program (Mich.); Women social reformers--United States.; Women and peace.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Afro-Americans--Women.; Camping--1921-1930.; Clothing and dress.; Demonstrations.; Dwellings.; Exhibitions.; India.; Indian women--North America.; International Congress of Women (1915: Hague, Netherlands); Machine shops.; Morgan, Angela, 1874-1957.; Netherlands.; Pacifism.; Pacifists.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Shelley, Rebecca, 1887-1984.; Shelley family.; Slogans.; Typewriters.; Women.; Women--Organizations.
Sound recordings
Shelley, Rebecca, 1887-1984.; Pacifism.; Pacifists.; Johnston, Margaret.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
Contributors:
Addams, Jane, 1860-1935.; American Association for a Democratic Germany.; Angell, Norman, Sir, 1874-1967.; Arnori, M. S.; Balch, Emily Greene, 1867-1961.; Baldwin, Roger N. (Roger Nash), 1884-1981; Bentley, Alvin M. (Alvin Morell), 1918-1969.; Boulding, Kenneth E. (Kenneth Ewart), 1910-1993; Breckinridge, Sophonisba Preston, 1866-1948.; Brown, Garry Eldridge, 1923-1998; Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Circle Pines Center.; Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Crane, Henry Hitt, 1890-1977.; Davis, John W. (John William), 1873-1955.; Dende, Leopold.; Detzer, Dorothy, 1893-1981.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Dougherty, Peter, 1805-1894.; Dubina, Nestor.; Eddy, Robert M.; Eldred, Mary.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Florence, Barbara Moench.; Florence, Philip.; Florer, Warren Washburn, 1869-1958.; Gage-Colby, Ruth.; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940.; Gray, Harold Studley, 1894-1972.; Hamilton, Alice, 1869-1970.; Harrington, Donald Szantho.; Harrison, Alice.; Hassler, Alfred.; Hays, Arthur Garfield, 1881-1954.; Herz, Alice.; Herz, Helga.; Heymann, Lida Gustava, 1868-1943.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Holbrook, Florence, 1860-1932.; Holmes, John Haynes, 1879-1964.; Huebsch, B. W. (Benjamin W.), 1876-1964.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Hutchinson, Paul, 1890-1956.; Johansen, August E. (August Edgar), 1905-1995; Kamarck, Esther.; Kamarck, Frank.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; Kresge, Sebastian Spering, 1867-1966.; Labadie, Jo, 1850-1933.; Laubach, Frank Charles, 1884-1970.; Lehman, Barbara.; Lindsey, Fanny Cole.; Lloyd, Lola Maverick, 1875-1944.; Lloyd, William B., Jr.; Lochner, Louis Paul, 1887-1975.; Lynch, Frederick Henry, 1867-1934.; Magsaysay, Ramon, 1907-1957.; Mazey, Emil, 1913-1983; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Minkoff, Lynn.; Morgan, Angela, 1874-1957.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Mygatt, Tracy D. (Tracy Dickinson), 1885-1973.; Nearing, Scott, 1883-1983.; Nielson, Axel.; Niemðoller, Martin, 1892-; O'Brien, Patrick H. (Patrick Henry), 1868-1959; O'Connor, Jessie Lloyd, 1904-; Olmsted, Mildred Scott, 1890-1990.; Paul, Alice, 1885-1977.; Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994; Puri, J. N.; Randall, Mercedes.; Rathmer, Felix Martin, d. 1959.; Reynolds, Barbara.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970.; Schwimmer, Franciska, 1880-1963.; Schwimmer, Rosika, 1877-1948.; Secor, Lella Faye, d. 1966.; Selskosojus, Inc.; Sexton, Kripp.; Shafer, Paul W. (Paul Werntz), 1893-1954.; Shapiro, Samuel.; Shelly, Edna.; Shelly, Florence.; Shelly, Paul.; Shelly, Will.; Shelly, William Alfred, 1854-1930.; Shibata, Shingo, 1930-; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968.; Staebler, Neil, 1905-2000; Steinson, Barbara J., 1948-; Sugar, Maurice, 1891-1974.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Todd, Paul Harold, 1921-2008; Turn Toward Peace (Organization); United States Farmers Association.; Van Koevering, Adrian, 1874-1960.; Villard, Fanny Garrison, 1844-1928.; Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1949.; War Resisters League.; Weinberger, Harry, 1888-; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.; Wilson, Charles Carroll.; Witherspoon, Frances M., 1886-1973.; Women Strike for Peace.; Women's International League for Peace and Freedom.; Woodruff, Alice.; Wynner, Edith.
- Biographical
  Biographical is a small series of only ten folders. Included are vitae, letterheads of organizations with which Shelley worked, transcripts of class presentations, a biographical sketch, and several oral history transcripts. The biographical sketch prepared by Janet Reedy for Jane Fonda and Columbia Pictures in 1980 is especially broad, covering Shelley's life beginning with childhood.
  - Vitae and Letterheads (Box 1)
  - Visit to a class at Western Michigan University, 1975; 4 pages (Box 1)
  - Biographical sketch prepared by Janet Reedy for Jane Fonda and Columbia Pictures, 1980; 23 pages (Box 1)
- Newspaper clippings
  Newspaper Clippings is also a small series, containing only nine folders. It is arranged chronologically and provides useful background information. Most articles are about World War I pacifist movement, Shelley's repatriation case, Peaceways, Shelley's Vietnam protests, or her trips abroad.
  - Pre-1915, 1915-1984; 9 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence is extensive (5.5 linear feet) and has been divided into two subseries based upon date of accessioning, 1974 and 1984. Both subseries are arranged chronologically. The two correspondence subseries were not interfiled because parts of the 1974 accession were microfilmed before the 1984 accession arrived. Although the accession groups overlap to a large extent, the 1974 accession is weighted before 1960 and the 1984 accession after 1950. The correspondence is notable for the letters exchanged with many leading pacifist, radical, religious, and political leaders. These include Jane Addams, Emily Balch, Emma Goldman, John Haynes Holmes, Jo Labadie, Scott Nearing, Alice Paul, Rosika Schwimmer, Upton Sinclair, Norman Thomas, Oswald Garrison Villard, and Wendell Willkie. Partial indices to correspondents have been prepared for both accession groups and are appended to this finding aid.
  - Accession, 1974
    - Undated, 1910-September 1928; 19 folders (Box 1)
      (Microfilm copy available of correspondence, 1915-1919)
    - October 1928-May 1938, 32 folders (Box 2)
    - June 1938-June 1954, 34 folders (Box 3)
    - July 1954-December 1961, 35 folders (Box 4)
  - Accession, 1984
    - Undated, 1911-1961; 28 folders (Box 5)
    - 1962-1975, 27 folders (Box 6)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 7)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 7)
    - 1980-1984 (Box 7)
- Topical Files
  Topical Papers encompasses two linear feet of material and is arranged alphabetically. This series was created out of papers which were identifiable with a particular organization, event, or person. Within this series are files relating to Shelley's efforts to regain her citizenship after losing it in 1922. These files include legal documents, drafts of letters, notes used by Shelley in court, and her written accounts of the proceedings. Administrative papers of the Rebecca Shelley Repatriation Committee are also included. There are news bulletins, a 1936 financial report, and papers of W.W. Denton, chairman, and Eleanor Williams, secretary. Additional information on Shelley's repatriation can be found in the Correspondence and Papers Of Other Individuals series.
  Also in this series, filed under Federal Writers Project, are files that document Shelley's work as a writer for the W.P.A.-sponsored project in the 1930s. The first three folders are made up primarily of writers' union records. The records of the American Federation of Government Employees #322 include registration rolls, minutes, and printed materials, all dated July 1937. United Office of Professional Workers of America, Local 26, replaced A.F.G.E. #322 in 1938 and these records include minutes and press releases. The last three folders in the subseries consist of Shelley's writings on the history of Germans in Michigan. In addition to descriptions of German immigrant influence, there is a long, personal narrative by Henry Becker titled, "My Story As An Immigrant."
  The Fellowship of Reconciliation files within the Topical Papers series, though consisting only of three folders, is especially strong. As was noted in the scope and content note, many of the Michigan F.O.R.'s early records came into Shelley's possession when she became editor of the newsletter in 1958. Though much of this material was removed to the separate F.O.R. collection, additional materials were accessioned in 1984 and these remain with the Shelley papers. The subseries is arranged chronologically from 1944-1969. The strongest material is located in the first folder, which contains the contents of a loose-leaf binder dated 1944-1947. This binder includes minutes of the Michigan F.O.R. executive council and state meetings, attendance sheets, mailing lists, flyers, announcements, treasurer's reports, correspondence, and regional and state chairman's reports.
  The Fanny Cole Lindsey file within the Topical Papers series contains papers, 1946-1947, relating to efforts by Shelley to stop an attempt to commit her friend Fanny Cole Lindsey to a mental hospital. The Angela Morgan file contains papers, 1957-1960, concerning Shelley's dispute with Frank and Esther Kamarck over placement of Angela Morgan's papers. Also in this file are poems and essays by Shelley written in tribute to Angela Morgan after Morgan's death. Most material relating to Morgan was removed to the separate Angela Morgan collection which was given by Shelley to the Michigan Historical Collections. The Peaceways Foundation files, 1959-1964, document Shelley's efforts to turn her Battle Creek farm into an international peace center. Included are minutes, by-laws, articles of incorporation, and an account book. There are also some papers from Peaceways International Indian Section, which Shelley established with J.N. Puri while traveling in the Far East.
  - American Association for the United Nations, 1951-1963 (Box 7)
  - Citizenship Case
    - Undated, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - 1931-1933 (Box 7)
    - 1936 (Box 7)
    - 1937-1939 (Box 7)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 7)
    - Accession, 1984; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Printed (Box 7)
  - Conner Estate, 1944-1946; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Federal Writers Project
    - Undated (Box 7)
    - American Federation of Government Employees, 1937 (Box 7)
    - United Office and Professional Workers of America, 1938 (Box 7)
    - History of Germans in Michigan, 1938~, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation
    - Notebook, 1944-1947 (Box 7)
    - 1945-1959, undated (Box 7)
    - 1960-1969, undated (Box 7)
    - Financial and Legal, 1927-1981 (Box 7)
    - Gandhi Peace Foundation, 1962-1968 (Box 8)
    - Lindsey, Fanny Cole (Box 8)
    - Mailing Lists (Box 8)
    - Michigan International Council, circa 1978 (Box 8)
    - Morgan, Angela, 1957-1960 (Box 8)
    - N.A.A.C.P.-Battle Creek, 1960-1965 (Box 8)
    - New Democrats of Michigan, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Peaceways Foundation
      - 1959-1964 (Box 8)
      - 1965-1976, undated (Box 8)
    - Pennfield Township Schools, 1946-1948 (Box 8)
    - Religious Society of Friends (mostly "Ann Arbor Friends Meeting" newsletters)
      - 1958-1968 (Box 8)
      - 1969-1981, undated (Box 8)
    - South Asian Expedition, 1970-1973
      - Personal Papers, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous Papers, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Poetry and Essays concerning South Asia (Box 8)
    - Turn Toward Peace, 1962-1963 (Box 8)
      (includes staff report, May 1963, manual for instructors of peace interns 1963 two issues of Alternatives, minutes, and several memos)
    - Wilson, Charles Carroll, 1961-1966; 2 folders (Box 8)
      (numerous essays and pamphlets by the founder of the cityist plan, also extensive correspondence 1963-1966)
    - Women Strike for Peace, 1961-1968 (Box 8)
      (mostly materials of the Ann Arbor and Detroit Women for Peace)
    - Women's International Democratic Federation, 1964-1968 (Box 8)
      (several national publications on Vietnam, the Dominican Republic and general subjects)
    - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom International Congress and Early Years, 1915-1918
      - Michigan Branch
        (some materials from Rouge Valley, Battle Creek, and Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti branches interfiled)
        - 1938-1959 (Box 8)
        - 1960-1965 (Box 8)
        - 1967-1978, undated (Box 8)
      - Historical Sketches (Box 8)
    - World Peace Month, 1955-1956; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - World Peace Study Mission (to Japan) (includes proposal, final report, and numerous pamphlets), 1963 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous Papers
  Miscellaneous is a series of non-correspondence, non-foldered material (when received) that has been arranged chronologically. The contents of the files related to all of Shelley's interests and activities.
  - Undated, 1913-1965; 23 folders (Box 9)
    (1974 accession)
  - Undated, unprocessed, 1915-1983; 4 folders (Box 9)
    (1984 accession; includes minutes of the People's Council and 1915 pledge signed by S.S. Kresge)
- Papers of other individuals
  Papers Of Other Individuals is a small series (two inches) of papers created by six other individuals but which came to be in Shelley's possession. The Emily Greene Balch papers consist of letters sent by Balch to various persons while serving as chairman of Rebecca Shelley's repatriation committee. The papers run from 1935-1937 and correspondents include John J. Bowman, John Safran, Charles Knott, Felix Frankfurter, W.W. Denton, and Oswald Garrison Villard. Although undated correspondence between Balch and Shelley is found in this folder, there is also extensive correspondence between the two women in the Correspondence series. The Richard Olsen series is a journal kept during 1977 and 1978 by Olsen while a resident at Shelley's Peaceways Foundation. It provides useful insight into the problems which led to the demise of Peaceways as a commune. The Felix Rathmer papers consist of two folders. The first is made up of his correspondence, mostly postcards, from 1911-1914 while a resident of Pittsfield, Massachusetts. The second folder is made up of papers from 1921-1951, mostly relating to his naturalization and electrical engineering business. The Kripp Sexton papers are made up of one envelope of notes which were left in his room after staying with Shelley. The Paul Shelly papers consist mostly of his correspondence in 1973 while trying to locate Rebecca who was traveling in South Asia at the time. There is also a ten-page autobiographical sketch written in 1977 and a genealogy of the Shelly Family. The papers of Rebecca Shelley's father, William Alfred Shelly, include a 1904 letter from a Saginaw land salesman encouraging him to move to Michigan and a 1918 letter from his son Will informing his father that he has enlisted in the Navy. There are also two diaries, 1906 and 1910, which document his work as an Evangelical minister. William Shelly was pastor at ten Michigan cities: Leelanau (1905-1907), Riverton (1907-1909), Traverse City (1909-1912), Park (1912-1914), Chesaning (1914-1918), Whittaker (1918-1922), Greenwood (1922-1924), Mt. Pleasant (1924-1926), Coleman (1926-1928), and Oregon (1928-1929).
  - Balch, Emily Greene, 1937 (Box 9)
  - Olsen, Richard, 1977-1978 (Box 9)
  - Rathmer, Felix Martin
    - 1911-1914 (Box 9)
    - 1921-1951 (Box 9)
  - Sexton, Kripp, undated (Box 9)
  - Shelly, Paul C., 1968-1977 (Box 9)
  - Shelly, William Alfred, 1890-1920 (Box 9)
- Printed
  The Printed series measures nearly five linear feet and is arranged chronologically from 1900 to 1984. Included in this series are pamphlets, flyers, books, and other printed works which Shelley accumulated. These materials cover a tremendous range of organizations and events and are a rich source for researchers of radical, pacifist, and feminist causes.
  - Undated, 1900-1927; 27 folders (Box 10)
  - 1928-1943, 22 folders (Box 11)
  - 1944-1955, 26 folders (Box 12)
  - 1956-1964, 27 folders (Box 13)
  - 1965-1984, 20 folders (Box 14)
- Periodicals
  Periodicals measures two linear feet and is arranged alphabetically by title of the publication. The contents list includes a complete list, titles and dates for the periodicals included in this series.
  - "Action Memorandum,", 1952; 3 issues (Box 14)
  - "The Appeal,", 1951-1953 (Box 14)
    vol. 1 no. 1 through vol. 2 no. 1 (complete)
  - "Between the Lines,", 1954-1957 (Box 14)
    scattered issues
  - "The Blaze,", 1950-1956 (Box 14)
  - "Canadian Far Eastern Newsletter,", 1955-1960 (Box 14)
  - "Committee for Nonviolent Action Bulletin,", 1961-1965 (Box 14)
  - "The Conscientious Objector,", 1941-1944 (Box 14)
  - "Counter-Spy,", May-Fall 1973 (Box 14)
  - "Czechoslovak Woman,", September-December 1965 (Box 14)
  - "Democratic German Report,", 1954-1967 (Box 15)
  - "Facts About Occupied Germany,", 1945-1948; 8 issues (Box 15)
  - "The Federalist,", 1963; 3 issues (Box 15)
  - "Fellowship,", 1938-1948; 4 issues (Box 15)
  - "For Peace on Earth,", 1954-1955; 4 issues (Box 15)
  - "Friendship Universal,", 1964-1965; 3 issues (Box 15)
  - "GI's Act," (vol. 1 no. 1-vol. 1 no. 3), circa 1967 (Box 15)
  - "God and Caesar,", 1976-1977; 2 issues (Box 15)